Well, this is the moment you have been waiting for.
It's time to code and create some of our first scripts.
Well, technically we have already created our first script as we did in the previous lesson, but this
time it'll be better.
But before we do, you might be asking yourself, well, what even is a script?
The short answer is A script is just blocks of code that are connected together that tell our sprite
what to do.
Like I described earlier, it's instructions for the computer.
So just as we have seen, one block of code is just a block of code.
But when we combine it, we get amazing things to happen, like the script which gets our cat to walk
to the end of the screen.
However, there is one key piece of the puzzle we are missing before we can officially call.
Our code blocks a script, and the key piece is located under the events group.
It's this when the flag is clicked.
You will see now that we can drag this code block to the start of our walking script.
And now when we click this green flag, our script plays.
No need to manually click on it, but that is just the beginning because you are not a programmer yet,
there is still one thing you need to do.
It's pretty much a rite of passage.
Once you've done this, you can officially call yourself a programmer.
Tell all your friends you're a programmer.
Tell your your dog you're a programmer, whoever you want to tell.
So move down to the looks code group.
Drag in the site and connect it to when the flag clicked.
Now for the most important step.
Are you ready?
Type in hello world!
Okay.
Done.
Now click play.
And there you have it.
Hello world.
You have created the most classic, iconic first program of all time.
You are now officially a programmer.
No one else can tell you otherwise.
So with that out of the way, let's make cool scripts and play with some of the blocks.
Once again, I am going to drag in this when flag clicked block, and this time I'm going to go up to
motions and play with some of the code here.
Let's try.
When flag clicked, move ten steps and turn 15 degrees.
Now when we click the flag, our cat moves the turns and it says hello world.
That's pretty cool.
But before we carry on, I don't know if you noticed, but our cat is doing a lot more turning and a
lot less moving, so how can we fix this?
Well, before I just go ahead and fix it, I want you to try and fix it.
Remember, learning happens in the doing so try to see if you can get this cat to move more than turn.
I'll be waiting.
Pause the video and give it a try.
Well, I hope you've figured it out, but even if you didn't, that's no problem.
So if you remember from earlier, we changed what our cat said simply by clicking on this text here
and typing in our new words.
And we can do the same thing for a movement and really everything else in scratch.
This is a very important thing to remember.
Almost all of the code blocks in scratch are customizable and they allow us to change their values.
Just scrolling down, you can see how I could change what costume is selected or what sound gets played.
This really gives us a lot more control on what happens.
So for our problem of moving more, all I have to do is change it to 20 steps.
Now, as you can see, when we click the flag, our cat moves in a much wider circle.
But let's not stop there.
Let's bring in some other cool code blocks.
Let's bring in this go to random position and I hope you can guess what this does.
Well, moving it onto our script, you can see that our cat jumps around the screen moving in pretty
different positions.
Pretty cool.
But let's try something better.
How about this glide to a random position.
What I'll do here is disconnect the script from when start clicked and connect this new block.
In this way, this script won't run.
But now, as you can see, when we click the flag, the cat glides to random positions on the screen,
which is pretty neat.
But the only annoying thing is how we have to keep clicking this flag.
Instead of doing that, we could bring in this repeat block like we did earlier and put this code inside
the block.
This way the code will repeat ten times.
Now, even when we click it again, our cat automatically runs around the screen.
Now, although it's a bit slow.
So what we could do is change the number of seconds from 1 to 0.2.
Now that's what I'm talking about.
I can't zooms around the screen, although our cat does eventually stop.
So how can we make it go on forever?
Or at least until we click the stop button?
Any ideas?
You see if you can figure out how to make the cat keep on moving forever, that's a clue.
Pause the video and see if you can do it.
Well, I hope you figured this one out, because to make our cat keep on moving around, all we have
to do is use the forever loop.
And basically any code that is in this loop will repeat forever.
Cool.
So switching it out and pressing play again, you can see that our cat just continually moves around
the screen like a crazy thing.
Okay, now, instead of having our cat just move around randomly, what if we want it to follow our
mouse?
Now that would be fun.
You get it?
Cat and mouse okay.
Yeah, yeah.
Pretty funny.
Right?
To make the cat chase the mouse, we can bring in this.
Go to code block and change it from a random position to a mouse pointer.
However, if we click play, you'll see nothing really happens.
Our cat just kind of moves to the corner of our screen.
But I want you to think about this now.
Why is our cat just moving to the edge of the screen?
Why is it not following the mouse?
I want you to fix this code and tell me when you're done, okay?
Of course I won't be able to hear you.
It's a computer screen and you're talking to.
And I'm not Dora the Explorer.
But let me know when you're done anyways.
A clue.
The solution is linked to a code block we just looked at.
So pause this and give it a go.
Fixed it.
Cool.
Or if you didn't, that's also cool as long as you tried.
Throughout our lessons, I will always give you opportunities to try and do things before I show you.
Remember that learning what happens in the trying.
So always try, even if you don't get it right.
But basically what's happening here is our sprite is going to our mouse, but it only does it once and
it only does it when we click our green flag.
So to fix this, all we need to do is put the go to mouse code block in a forever loop.
And this time we click play and you'll see it works.
And it's pretty cool.
As you can see, it doesn't matter how fast I move the mouse, the cat will always keep up.
And this works because our sprite is forever going to our mouse pointer, not just when we click play.
Okay, let's try one more script.
Before we wrap up this lesson, let's grab this point towards block here.
And I'm guessing you have an idea of what this does because as you can see it has mouse pointer selected
meaning our sprite will point towards our mouse.
Let's also grab another code block and this time from the looks group here.
Let's bring in this change color effect by 25.
And like before, we'll put both these code blocks in a forever loop.
That way it doesn't just do it once or so.
We will add in this when the flag click to complete the code right.
Let's give this a go.
As you can see, our cat has turned into an RGB keyboard and is constantly pointing towards our mouse.
Yeah, nice.
Okay, that's all for this lesson.
We covered quite a lot and I'm sure you learned a lot.
Now, I just want you to take this moment to write some of your own script.
Just experiment with different code blocks and see what they do, and I'll see you in the next lesson.
So have some fun.